## **Alexander Smith**

Technical Support Engineer and System Administrator

shadowhunter@gmail.com

## Summary

An effective UNIX, Linux and Windows system administrator, with aspirations to be a part of a large and prominent services provider team. I have experience maintaining servers in an enterprise data center environment at the component and rack level. I have 15+ years experience in the IT field, and have used systems ranging from a Commodore 64 to HP mainframes. I've maintained x86/x64, Power Architecture (IBM POWER and PowerPC), as well as SPARC servers. Specialties: Linux, UNIX and Windows administration. Desktop and server troubleshooting, repair and field break/fix support.

## Experience

#### Consulting System Administrator at DetectRight

May 2008 - Present (7 years 3 months)

Remotely maintain Linux production servers as a consultant. Troubleshoot firewall rules and optimize performance of LAMP stack.

1 recommendation available upon request

## System Integrator at New Dominion Technology

June 2001 - Present (14 years 2 months)

Build desktops and servers as a value-added reseller and system integrator. Provide various IT consulting and contract services as an OnForce Service Professional.

3 recommendations available upon request

#### Technical Support Engineer at BlackMesh

April 2015 - May 2015 (2 months)

Act as system administrator for customer servers to provide technical support for assorted customers.

#### Data Center Technician at Amazon.com

December 2010 - April 2013 (2 years 5 months)

Maintained a data center, providing hardware maintenance, break-fix and troubleshooting for servers and network devices. Troubleshoot HP, SGI, Rackable Systems, Dell and other manufacturers of equipment. Detect systemic faults that impact the server fleet, and escalate to proper team to ensure data integrity. Rack and stack server and network gear, as well as perform tasks as network engineers "remote hands" in troubleshooting physical connectivity with network switches, consisting of Cisco Catalyst and Cisco Nexus switches. Assist electricians and HVAC professionals as needed in tasks at the rack level to ensure server health and safety.

1 recommendation available upon request

#### Linux/AIX System Administrator (Contractor) at IBM Global Services

September 2008 - December 2009 (1 year 4 months)

Responsible for over 100 IBM "big iron" servers, consisting of system x and system p, running Red Hat Enterprise Linux and AIX. Appointed patch manager of our team, maintaining and certifying patches, while logging for proper audit compliance.

### Application Support Analyst at DaVita

October 2007 - December 2007 (3 months)

Provide helpdesk support for the in-house intake, discharge and operations software.

#### Customer Support Analyst (Contractor) at Motorola

April 2007 - September 2007 (6 months)

Provide break/fix support for the state of Tennessee for Motorola's line of Automated Fingerprint Identification Systems, including Livescan workstations and backend. Backend is running Red Hat Enterprise Linux, with JBoss as middleware for their custom web-based application. Provide on-site 9x5 support for the Tennessee Bureau of Investigation.

## Computer Lab Technician at Middle Tennessee State University

2002 - 2006 (4 years)

Maintain computer labs for the Computer Science department from 2002-2003 and the Health & Human Performance department in 2006. Perform minor maintenance and coordinate with internal IT department as well as support vendors.

## Associate System Administrator (Contractor) at Sheer Genius

January 2003 - March 2003 (3 months)

Maintain four Linux test and production servers, running Apache, MySQL, PHP and Cyrus. Deployed office workstations, researched and implemented trouble ticket system for internal and customer use.

## Skills & Expertise

Servers

**Data Center** 

**Server Management** 

Linux

**Apache** 

Solaris

**Red Hat Linux** 

**Amazon EC2** 

Hardware

**OpenSolaris** 

**Troubleshooting** 

**Cloud Computing** 

**Amazon Web Services (AWS)** 

TCP/IP

**HP Proliant** 

**Dell PowerEdge Servers** 

RHEL

Virtualization

**Shell Scripting** 

**AIX** 

**MySQL** 

**Firewalls** 

**Networking** 

**Vagrant** 

Unix

**Python** 

SaltStack

Git

**Asterisk** 

**DNS** 

**RAID** 

**Technical Support** 

**Switches** 

**ZFS** 

**DD-WRT** 

**VPN** 

**Network Security** 

**Routers** 

**Network Administration** 

**Network Design** 

Bash

**VirtualBox** 

**VMware ESXi** 

**Rackable Systems** 

3ware

MegaRAID

**IPMI** 

**Kickstart** 

**NFS** 

## Certifications

## Learning How to Learn: Powerful mental tools to help you master tough subjects

Coursera Verified Certificates License JXZ7JYLWDY February 2015

### **Programming for Everybody (Python)**

Coursera Verified Certificates License YXES2AYZL8 August 2014

## **Understanding Video Games**

Coursera Verified Certificates License 74M6PKYZHD December 2014

#### Gamification

Coursera Verified Certificates License V4F2B9GLB2 April 2014

#### **Concepts in Games Development**

Open2Study License 50491 November 2014

#### **Principles of Project Management**

Open2Study License 56010 December 2014

Server+

CompTIA License 16KMLXKJTCB1Q5MZ April 2010

Network+

CompTIA License NL960KXLKDBQ2FHC April 2010

#### Microsoft Desktop Support – ENTERPRISE

Microsoft License 917797 July 2010

#### **Amateur Radio License**

Federal Communications Commission License K4RNT June 2002 to October 2022

## **Projects**

#### Network device audit

January 2012 to April 2013

Members: Alexander Smith

Performed a complete site-wide audit of network switches and gear in network rooms. Cross-checked with network device location database, completed information on each device encountered. Improved technician productivity by reducing the amount of time needed to find a given network device.

#### **Elastic Block Store outage**

February 2011 to Present

Members: Alexander Smith, Taha Menai, Jeffrey Johnston, Apurva Solanki

Perform repairs on server fleet due to a large server outage affecting Amazon Web Services in the Elastic Block Store (EBS) service.

#### Wireless site surveys

January 2011 to Present

Members: Alexander Smith

Perform wi-fi site surveys for home and small businesses. Designed wi-fi upgrades for a popular restaurant and night venue in Sterling, Virginia.

#### **Desktop refresh for medical provider**

January 2012 to December 2013

Members: Alexander Smith

Refreshed desktops and laptops for a medical provider. The provider purchased a ThinkPad X series, and upgraded front office desktop that also operates as a server for the electronic medical record system.

#### Online media streaming service

June 2001 to October 2014

Members: Alexander Smith, John Carehag, Chris Abbott, Kenneth Mutka

Provide technical assistance on an ad-hoc basis for a record label specializing in computer and video game music. Operate a US-based relay for two online streaming radio stations specializing in computer and video game remixes and original compositions.

#### **Global Expense Reporting System**

September 2008 to December 2009

Members: Alexander Smith

Helped maintain a hosted web-based expense reporting solution for Fortune 500 companies.

### Palm acquisition as part of automated fingerprint collection

April 2007 to September 2007

Members: Alexander Smith, Richard Mackiewicz

Added functionality on livescan workstations to acquire palms in addition to tenprint scans, rolling out statewide as part of preventative and onsite maintenance calls. Upgraded backend processing servers to handle the additional data for acquisition and matching.

#### **Refresh of Sun workstations**

July 2002 to Present

Members: Alexander Smith

Performed refresh and reinstall of Solaris onto Sun Ultra 5, located in the Computer Science Department computer lab. Integrated with university-wide user directory and set up for specialized use.

## Volunteer Experience

## Event Volunteer (Technical Operations) at MAGfest

January 2011 - Present (4 years 7 months)

Provide operational assistance for the annual music and gaming festival, held in National Harbor, Maryland, near Washington DC. Provide assistance with Linux-based network solution, as well as working audio mixers and equipment.

#### **Emergency Communications Volunteer at Amateur Radio Emergency Service**

June 2002 - Present (13 years 2 months)

Provide communications assistance during disasters.

## Weather Spotter at Metro Skywarn, Inc

June 2002 - Present (13 years 2 months)

Provide expertise as a trained weather spotter and amateur radio operator. Provide communications expertise during major weather events, including the April 7, 2006 Tornado Outbreak that affected the Nashville, Tennessee metropolitan area, and 2008 Super Tuesday Tornado Outbreak.

## Infrastructure Working Group Member at Reverse Space

February 2011 - January 2014 (3 years)

Implemented a PXE boot system for CentOS 5.6, 6.0 and Scientific Linux 6.0, as part of a team. Implemented an Asterisk PBX phone system, using the FreePBX Distribution.

#### Boy Scout at Boy Scouts of America, Chief Seattle Council

June 1989 - June 1998 (9 years 1 month)

Achieved the rank of Life in Troop 404, Green River District, located in Kent, Washington. Held positions including Assistant Patrol Leader, Patrol Leader, Troop Librarian, Scribe and Den Chief for Cub Scout Pack 404.

#### Fire Explorer at Boy Scouts of America, Chief Seattle Council

June 1999 - June 2001 (2 years 1 month)

Was a Fire Explorer with the Pacific Fire Department, Station 39 in Pacific, Washington. Trained in fire sciences, firefighting technique, search and rescue, as well as advanced first aid and CPR. Rode along during firefighting calls, EMS callouts, as well as mass casualty incident drills across western Washington, interfacing with many other organizations, including the US Civil Air Patrol during direction finding exercises.

#### Courses

Coursera

Gamification

Programming for Everyone (Python)

Univ. of Michigan

Univ. of Alberta

UC San Diego

Think Ahead: How to Reason and Argue

Cloud Computing Concepts

University of Illinois

#### **Information Technology**

Cascadia Community College

Network Design Concepts (Cisco) BIT 102

### Computer Engineering Technology/Technician

Middle Tennessee State University

Intro to Electricity and Electronics

Elementary Japanese II

Intro to Metals and Metallurgy

Audio for Media

Electrical Circuit Analysis (DC)

Computer Science II

ET 3610

JAPN 1020

ET 1210

RIM 3010

ET 3601

CSCI 2170

#### **Network Support Administration**

Daymar Institute-Murfreesboro

Principles of Psychology PSY 202
CompTIA A+ Core NSA 150

| CompTIA A+ OS (Windows)           | NSA 151 |
|-----------------------------------|---------|
| CompTIA Network+                  | NSA 152 |
| CompTIA Server+                   | NSA 155 |
| Administering a Windows Client OS | NSA 260 |
| Administering a Windows Server OS | NSA 261 |
| Troubleshooting OS & Networks     | NSA 266 |

Open2Study

Concepts in Games Development GameDev.14.10.20

Principles of Project Management ProjMgt
Emergency Management Emergncy

### Diploma, Vocational studies

Kentwood High School

Materials Science and Engineering

AP Computer Science (C++)

Computer Programming I (Pascal)

Japanese I/II

Japanese III/IV

Computers in Business II (HTML)

Computer Repair and Troubleshooting (CompTIA A+)

Principles of Technology

Computer Repair and Troubleshooting (Teaching

Assistant)

Special Topics in Computer Science (Linux)

**AP Music Theory** 

**AP Economics** 

Computer Programming II/III (C++)

## **Test Scores**

### **CEEB Foreign Language Test - Japanese**

December 2001 Score:PASS

Entered JAPN 1020 directly out of high school at Middle Tennessee State University, scored high enough for instructor to enter additional credit for JAPN 1010 by course challenge in 2001.

## **American College Test**

March 2001 Score:26

Achieved a composite score of 26 on the ACT college entrance examination.

## **AP Computer Science AB**

June 2000 Score: 2/4

Insufficient score to gain college credit, but enough to gain instructor permission to enter directly into CSCI 2170 at Middle Tennessee State University.

#### **AP Microeconomics**

December 2000 Score: 2/4

#### **AP Macroeconomics**

December 2000 Score: 2/4

### **AP Music Theory**

December 1999 Score: 2/4

### Honors and Awards

#### **Dean's List**

Daymar Institute-Murfreesboro

August 2010

Earned a GPA between 3.0 and 3.5 during the Summer 2010 quarter.

#### **President's List**

Daymar Institute-Murfreesboro

May 2010

Earned a GPA between 3.5 and 4.0 for the Spring 2010 quarter.

#### **President's List**

Daymar Institute-Murfreesboro

August 2009

Earned a GPA between 3.5 and 4.0 during the Summer 2009 quarter.

## Languages

## Japanese

## Education

#### Coursera

2013 - 2017

### Open2Study

2014 - 2016

## **FEMA Emergency Management Institute**

Crisis/Emergency/Disaster Management, 2003 - 2016

### **Daymar Institute-Murfreesboro**

Network Support Administration, 2009 - 2010

Grade: 3.5/4.0

## **Middle Tennessee State University**

Computer Engineering Technology/Technician, 2001 - 2010

Activities and Societies: Raider Radio Club, Association of Computing Machinery (MTSU chapter),

Association of Information Technology Professionals

1 recommendation available upon request

#### **Nashville State Community College**

Professional Studies: Information Technology, 2007 - 2009

### **Cascadia Community College**

Information Technology, 2001 - 2001

## **Kentwood High School**

Diploma, Vocational studies, 1998 - 2001

Grade: 2.88/4.0

Activities and Societies: Key Club, Kent Schools Judo Club, String Orchestra, Japan Club, Anime Club

### **Interests**

Amateur radio, electronics, new technologies, JFS, XFS, Linux, Solaris, ZFS, AIX and QNX. Smart card programming, RFID and multi-factor authentication using hardware tokens and smart cards. Vintage computing and retro gaming. Amateur musician, interested in synthesizer programming, computer and video game arrangement and remixing.

## Organizations

## Nashville Linux Users Group

January 2002 to Present

## Chattanooga Unix, GNU and Linux Users Group (CHUGALUG)

August 2008 to Present

### Southeast 2600 Organization

September 2008 to Present

Volunteered at the annual PhreakNIC computer and security conference, held annually in Nashville, Tennessee.

#### Northern Virginia Linux Users Group

January 2011 to Present

#### The Geek Group

2007 to Present

# **Alexander Smith**

Technical Support Engineer and System Administrator

shadowhunter@gmail.com



## 6 people have recommended Alexander

"Alex taught me things I never knew about Linux :)"

- Chris Abbott, was Alexander's client

"Alex is extremely knowledgeable in the UNIX/AIX/Linux field. He assisted me with setting up several Sun servers at my home for my personal use and offered helpful technology presentations as a member of the Nashville Linux Users Group (NLUG). Helpful to the end, Alex will always be a valuable member to NLUG and to any company that he works for."

## — Kevin Eldridge, was Alexander's client

"Alex was a very energetic and positive employee. He was always eager to try something new. His attitude was quite refreshing."

— Matt Kenigson, CSM, Owner, Sheer Genius, Inc., managed Alexander at Black Wolf Technologies (formerly Sierra One Computer Services)

"Alexander's experience with multiple platforms and multiple generations of equipment makes him uniquely qualified as a systems administrator for small to medium companies."

#### — Wylie Smith, was Alexander's client

"Alex possesses a strong toolset of facts and knowledge and can solve unique problems many do not consider. His \*nix related skills are superb and he has a wealth of knowledge in many obscure (however very useful) fields. As such he is a key asset on anyone's team and I would definitely recommend him."

— **Jeffrey Johnston**, *Datacenter Technician*, *CORESTAFF Services for Amazon.com*, worked directly with Alexander at Amazon.com

"He is heavy linux user and very good linux teacher."

— Nan Chen, Graduate Research Assistant, Middle Tennessee State University, studied with Alexander at Middle Tennessee State University

Contact Alexander on LinkedIn